Guide to the Ward Shepard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Ward Shepard papers
1909-1959
MS 746
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
(5 boxes)
Correspondence, writings and a few essays by others on ecology, Indians, and Darwinism. The main portion of the correspondence (1943-1958) is with John Collier on the subject of Shepard's last book, The Living Whole. His writings reflect interests in the environment and related scientific subjects, and the papers include both published and unpublished works.
Shepard, Ward, 1887-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These papers originally formed a portion of the John Collier Papers in the Yale University Library, and were separated when the Collier Papers were processed.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1930-1959. II. Writings, 1934-1957. III. Writings of Others, 1909-1956.
Scope and Contents
The Ward Shepard Papers consist of his correspondence and writings, as well as some writings of others. These papers were discovered among the John Collier Papers when the collection was processed. They represent only a small segment of the varied life and career of Ward Shepard.
The papers have been arranged in three series. Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, is largely that of Shepard to Collier regarding his progress on an unpublished book, The Living Whole.
Series II, WRITINGS, is divided into unpublished and published work. Among the unpublished materials are articles dealing with evolution, ecology and other scientific subjects; drafts and outlines for chapters of The Living Whole; memoranda, prepared during Shepard's years in government service (1943-1950); and notes on various subjects including energy, evolution, nature, philosophy, psychology, science and teleology. The final section of unpublished material contains a number of unidentified and undated papers on a variety of topics. These appear to be proposed articles or addresses written by Shepard after his retirement. The published material consists of reprints of articles and book reviews published by Shepard in various scientific magazines.
Series III, WRITINGS OF OTHERS, contains articles and writings by John Collier, Laura Thompson and others in the field of sociology and soil conservation.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Ward Shepard was born in Hicksville, Ohio, in 1887. He graduated from Harvard College in 1910 and received his master's degree from the Harvard Forest School in 1913. He married Jean Francis Duer Key on 12 October 1918. From 1921 to 1927 Shepard worked for the United States Forest Service as a forest ranger and a forest supervisor in the Western National Forests. While working for the Forest Service, he contributed his own knowledge to the planning of a nation-wide federal forest research program.
In 1932, Ward Shepard was appointed a fellow of the Carl Schurz Memorial Foundation. This afforded him the opportunity to make an extensive study of forestry practices, policies and legislation in central Europe. Upon his return to the United States, in 1933, Shepard became an economic advisor to John Collier, the U.S. Commissioner of Indian Affairs. During his three years with the Bureau of Indian Affairs, Shepard, like Collier, supported a policy of fair treatment of the Indians. He helped draft the Wheeler-Howard Indian Reorganization Act while on the Bureau's staff. Like many others interested in Indian reform, he hoped that this act would change past concepts of Indian administration and develop a new program of Indian land conservation and rehabilitation designed to safeguard Indian lands for Indian agriculture, livestock raising and forestry.
On 1 May 1936, President James B. Conant of Harvard University named Ward Shepard director of the Harvard Forest School. In this capacity, Shepard undertook the strengthening and expansion of forestry education at Harvard. The school trained students in the biological aspects of forestry and also provided knowledge in the more complex economic, legislative and financial areas of forestry for those conservationists interested in implementing programs to end the wholesale liquidation of forests in the United States.
After Shepard completed his work at Harvard, he returned to Washington in 1939 as a special advisor on forest policy for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. In 1940, he rejoined the Office of Indian Affairs as an advisor on natural resources development. He continued to be an outspoken advocate of the Soil Conservation Service. To dramatize the need for preserving farmland, he wrote the book, Food or Famine; The Challenge of Erosion, in 1945.
Towards the end of his life, Shepard became increasingly involved in scientific and philosophical writing. At the time of his death, in 1959, he was working on a book, The Living Whole, which dealt with Darwin and evolutionary theory. Ward Shepard died on his farm in Oakton, Virginia, on 13 September 1959.
Conservation of natural resources; Ecology; Environmental protection; Indians of North America; Soil conservation; Collier, John, 1884-1968; Shepard, Ward, 1887-1959
- Correspondence, 1930-1959; Series I; .1 linear foot (4 folders)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, CORRESPONDENCE, is largely that of Shepard to Collier regarding his progress on an unpublished book, The Living Whole. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, 1930-1959.
  - 1930 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1950-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings, 1934-1957; Series II; 2 linear feet (5 boxes)
  Series II, WRITINGS, is divided into unpublished and published work. Among the unpublished materials are articles dealing with evolution, ecology and other scientific subjects; drafts and outlines for chapters of The Living Whole; memoranda, prepared during Shepard's years in government service (1943-1950); and notes on various subjects including energy, evolution, nature, philosophy, psychology, science and teleology. The final section of unpublished material contains a number of unidentified and undated papers on a variety of topics. These appear to be proposed articles or addresses written by Shepard after his retirement. The published material consists of reprints of articles and book reviews published by Shepard in various scientific magazines. The series is arranged in five sections; articles; books; memoranda; notes; typescripts. There is one section of published reprints and reviews following the unpublished materials. Within each section items are organized chronologically, followed by the undated materials, which are arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Articles
    - Theory of Value, 1946 March (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Social Ecology, 1949 February 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Old Worlds and New: The Crisis of Mankind, 1950 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - The Living Whole
      - First draft, (1955?) (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Second draft, (1955?) (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Third draft, (1955?) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Books
    - Social Ecology
      - Draft of outline and synopsis, (1949) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - The Living Whole
      - Introduction and table of contents, 1954 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Chapter I, The Origin of a Scientific Myth, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Chapter II, The Granary of Life, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Chapter III, Man-made War of Nature, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Chapter IV, Plant Pioneers of Land Conquest, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Chapter V, Plant Architects of the Life Community, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Chapter VI, The Mosaic of Life, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Chapter VII, The Balance of Nature: War or System?, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Chapter VIII, The Biocentric Universe, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - The Living Whole
      - Chapter IX, System Laws of the Living Community, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Chapter X, Weak Links in Evolutionary Theory, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Chapter XI, The Cosmic Matrix of Order, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Chapter XII, The Field of Life, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Chapter XIII, The Life Web, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Chapter XIV, Man: The Primitive Order, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - Chapter XV, Man: The Civilized Order, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Chapter XVI, The New Commonwealth, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Chapter XVII, Man and Nature, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Memoranda
      - Report to the Secretary of the Interior on the Soil Erosion Service and on a Permanent Coordinated Program of Soil Erosion Control, 1934 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Food and Soil: A World Crisis introduction, Undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Food and Soil: A World Crisis, 1943 September 10 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - The Best of Two Worlds, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Government's role in a national science program, Undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Suggestions on proposed World Conservation Conference, Undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Total Conservation for Total Flood Control, Undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Notes
    - Science of Nature, (1946?) (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
    - The Structure and Dynamics of Community (syllabus of course taught by WS), 1930 January 30 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Predators, (1952?) (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Teleology, (1952?) (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Mind in Nature, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Chromosomes and Directed Evolution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Tentative Note on Energy and Matter, Undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Evolution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
    - Man and Nature, Undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
    - Origins of Social Cooperation, Undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
    - Patterns of Light, Undated (Box 4, Folder 48)
    - Notes on Philosophy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 49)
    - The Power of the Human Mind, Undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
    - Note on Probability and Random Motion, Undated (Box 4, Folder 51)
    - Psychology, Undated (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Typescripts
    - The Duty of the Government to Stop Forest Devastation, 1935 (Box 4, Folder 52a)
    - Modest Proposal for Peaceful Abdication of Capitalism, (1946?) (Box 4, Folder 53)
    - Nature Red in Tooth and Claw, 1953 March 26 (Box 4, Folder 54)
    - Atom Bomb, Undated (Box 4, Folder 55)
    - Authority Versus Humanity: A Study of Modern Social Conflict, Undated (Box 4, Folder 56)
    - The Blind Alley of the Social Sciences, Undated (Box 4, Folder 57)
    - The Candle's Beam, Undated (Box 4, Folder 58)
    - Creative Functional Evolution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 59)
    - The Darwinian Paradox, Undated (Box 4, Folder 60)
    - Liberalism, Undated (Box 4, Folder 61)
    - Life and Entropy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - The Malthusian Myth (draft), Undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
    - Life Out of Death, The Malthusian - Darwin Myth, Undated (Box 4, Folder 64)
    - The Meaning of Evolution, Undated (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - The Organism as Mental Process, Undated (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Private Enterprise and Native Cultures, Undated (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Science for Democracy, Undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - The Struggle for Existence, Undated (Box 5, Folder 69)
    - Toward a Field Theory, Undated (Box 5, Folder 70)
    - World War II, Undated (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Reprints and Reviews
    - "The Tools for Ethnic Democracy," Common Ground, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 72)
    - "Science for Democracy," Science, 1946 January 18 (Box 5, Folder 73)
    - "Our Indigenous Shangri-La," Scientific Monthly, 1946 February (Box 5, Folder 74)
    - Review by Ward Shepard of Culture in Crisis by Laura Thompson, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 75)
- Writings of Others, 1909-1956; Series III; .1 linear foot (8 folders)
  Series III, WRITINGS OF OTHERS, contains articles and writings by John Collier, Laura Thompson and others in the field of sociology and soil conservation. The series is arranged alphabetically by the author's name. There is one folder of newspaper clippings at the end of this series.
  - Extracts from "The Troubled Dream" by John Collier, 1956 November (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Outlines of classes given by John Collier, Undated (Box 5, Folder 77)
  - "Darwin's Influence Upon Philosophy" by John Dewey, 1909 July (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Reprints of articles in Journal of Soil and Water Conservation: Edward H. Graham, Seymour E. Harris, Edward A. Ackerman, 1946 October (Box 5, Folder 79)
  - Therapeutic Values in Navajo Religion Alexander and Dorothea Leighton, Undated (Box 5, Folder 80)
  - "Improvement of Forest Soil and Increase of Wood Production by Fertilization with Lime" by Heinrich Suchting, Undated (Box 5, Folder 81)
  - Extracts from Culture in Crisis: A Study of the Hopi Indians by Laura Thompson, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 82)